<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

<properties>
  <title>SAMP Kit</title>
  <author email="m.b.taylor@bristol.ac.uk">Mark Taylor</author>
</properties>

<body>
<section name="External Dependencies">

<p>SAMPKit is a pure Java library.  
It should run on any Java Runtime Environment of version J2SE1.4 or above.
</p>

<p>It currently has a single 
<a href="dependencies.html">dependency</a>, the Apache XML-RPC library.
In fact, not very much of this is used, and I am considering incorporating
the necessary functionality into SAMPKit itself.  This would reduce the
amount of code required at runtime, and possibly ameliorate class resolution
issues (e.g. for applications which need to use a different version of the
Apache XML-RPC library than the one required by SAMPKit).
Let me know if you're keen to see this option.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Internal Dependencies">

<p>If you are embedding SAMPKit into your own application code but want to
keep the size of the additional class files to a minimum, you can avoid
incorporating all of the classes in the built jar file.
The subordinate packages are arranged in a modular way.
They are organised as follows:
</p>
<dl>
<dt><a target="javadoc"
       href="apidocs/org/astrogrid/samp/package-summary.html"
                    >org.astrogrid.samp</a></dt>
<dd>Basic classes required throughout the library.  You need these
    whatever you're doing.
    </dd>
<dt><a target="javadoc"
       href="apidocs/org/astrogrid/samp/client/package-summary"
                    >org.astrogrid.samp.client</a></dt>
<dd>Classes intended for use by application authors writing SAMP clients.
    If you only need to run a SAMP hub, you do not need these classes.
    </dd>
<dt><a target="javadoc"
       href="apidocs/org/astrogrid/samp/hub/package-summary"
                    >org.astrogrid.samp.hub</a></dt>
<dd>Classes providing the hub implementation.
    If you are only writing a client which will not contain an embedded hub,
    you do not need these classes.</dd>
<dt><a target="javadoc"
       href="apidocs/org/astrogrid/samp/gui/package-summary"
                    >org.astrogrid.samp.gui</a></dt>
<dd>Utility classes providing GUI components for visual display of SAMP
    activity.  These classes are not required for basic client or hub
    operations.</dd>
<dt><a target="javadoc"
       href="apidocs/org/astrogrid/samp/test/package-summary"
                    >org.astrogrid.samp.test</a></dt>
<dd>Classes providing the hub test suite and some diagnostic tools intended
    for debugging SAMP systems.  These are not intended for use in third party
    applications.  This does not however contain unit tests for SAMPKit
    itself, which are not present in the distributed jar file.
    </dd>
</dl>

</section>
</body>

</document>
