<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

<properties>
  <title>JSAMP</title>
  <author email="m.b.taylor@bristol.ac.uk">Mark Taylor</author>
</properties>

<body>
<section name="JSAMP">

<p>JSAMP is a Java toolkit for use with the
<a href="http://www.ivoa.net/samp/"
   >Simple Applications Messaging Protocol</a>.
It provides the following components:
</p>
<ul>
<li>A SAMP hub implementation, suitable for standalone or embedded use</li>
<li>A set of classes which can be used to implement SAMP capabilities in
    client applications</li>
<li>A hub test and benchmarking suite, which can test correctness and
    performance of third-party hub implementations</li>
<li>Utilities which can be used by client and hub developers, or SAMP users,
    to analyse or debug SAMP sessions</li>
<li>Graphical components built on top of the basic functionality suitable
    for use with the above</li>
<li>A bridge component, which can allow clients on different hubs to
    talk to each other</li>
</ul>
<p>For a given purpose, some or all of these components may be used at one time.
</p>

<p>The toolkit's design aims are, in rough order of priority:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Correctness according to the SAMP standard</li>
<li>Robustness</li>
<li>Ease of use for client application authors</li>
<li>Ease of deployment within third-party applications (few dependencies)</li>
<li>Flexibility, including the possibility to use with non-<em>Standard</em>
    SAMP <em>Profiles</em></li>
<li>Good documentation</li>
<li>Small size <i>(this one's gone by the board a bit)</i></li>
</ul>

<p>The current version targets the SAMP 
<a href="http://www.ivoa.net/Documents/SAMP/20101216/"
   >1.2 Recommendation</a> document (16 December 2010);
this is very close to the
<a href="http://www.ivoa.net/Documents/cover/SAMP-20090421.html"
   >1.11 Recommendation</a> (21 April 2009),
but with an enhancement concerning Standard Profile hub discovery.
</p>

<p>JSAMP is currently developed by 
<a href="http://www.star.bristol.ac.uk/~mbt/">Mark Taylor</a>
(m.b.taylor@bristol.ac.uk), 
working in the
<a href="http://www.phy.bris.ac.uk/groups/astrophysics/">Astrophysics Group</a>
at
<a href="http://www.bristol.ac.uk/">Bristol University</a>.
It was originally developed within the UK's 
<a href="http://www.astrogrid.org/">AstroGrid</a> project,
and has also been supported by <a href="http://www.stfc.ac.uk/">STFC</a> 
grant ST/H008470/1 and by 
<a href="http://research.microsoft.com/">Microsoft Research</a>.
All of this support is gratefully acknowledged.
</p>

<p>Queries, bug reports, suggestions etc may be mailed to the author,
or raised on the 
<a href="http://www.ivoa.net/pipermail/apps-samp/">apps-samp@ivoa.net</a>
mailing list.
</p>

<p>JSAMP is open source software; it is available under (at least) the
Academic Free Licence and the BSD Licence.
</p>

</section>

</body>

</document>
