<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
          "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
          "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<document>

<properties>
  <title>Profiles</title>
  <author email="m.b.taylor@bristol.ac.uk">Mark Taylor</author>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Profiles">

<p>The SAMP protocol is defined in two parts, as an abstract API and
as transport-specific Profiles.
One or more Profiles may be offered for by a SAMP hub to allow clients
to communicate with it.
At present, JSAMP offers two basic profiles, the Standard Profile,
intended for normal desktop-based clients, 
and the Web Profile, intended for browser-based clients 
(some variants of these are also possible).
These are described below.
</p>

<p>By default, the hub is configured with both Standard and Web profiles
available, but only Standard Profile switched on by default.
If you want to use the Web Profile, either configure it to start using
command-line flags to the Hub command, or equivalent programmatic settings.
To switch on the Web Profile as well as the Standard Profile by default
in the hub, you can do one of the following:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Run the jsamp <code>hub</code> command
    with the <code>-profiles std,web</code> flag.</li>
<li>Run the hub, or whatever java program is going to start a JSAMP hub
    (e.g. TOPCAT, Aladin) with the system property flag
    <code>-Djsamp.hub.profiles=std,web</code>.</li>
<li>Check the checkbox in the the <b>Profiles|Web Profile</b> menu 
    in the hub GUI window.</li>
<li>Check the checkbox in the <b>Profiles|Web Profile</b> menu
    provided by clicking on the hub system tray icon.</li>
<li>If you're writing code, you can use one of the methods in the
    <a target="samp-javadoc"
       href="apidocs/org/astrogrid/samp/hub/Hub.html"
                                           >Hub</a> class
    which allow you to specify what profiles will be used.</li>
</ul>

<p>The <b>Profiles</b> menu in the hub window looks something like this:
</p>
<img src="images/ProfileMenu.png"
     alt="Screenshot of Profiles menu in the hub GUI window"/>
<p>and from the system tray icon something like this:
</p>
<img src="images/SystrayMenu.png"
     alt="Screenshot of Profiles menu in the system tray window"/>
<p>Checking one of the checkboxes has the effect of turning the 
profile in question on, and unchecking it turns it off.
When a profile is turned off, any clients registered using that profile
are forcibly ejected from the hub.
</p>

<subsection name="Standard Profile">

<p>The Standard Profile is intended for use by normal desktop tools.
Clients discover the location of the hub by looking in a file named
<code>.samp</code> in the user's home directory.
The fact that this file is normally only readable by the user running
the hub means that connections cannot be made by other users.
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Web Profile">

<p>The Web Profile is intended for use by web applications, that is,
programs or web pages running inside a web browser.
Web applications can find the hub at a well-known port.
When a web application wants to register, the hub will ask the user,
by popping up a dialogue window, whether the application should be
allowed to run.
The dialogue window will look something like this:
</p>
<img src="images/WebProfilePopup.png"
     alt="Web Profile popup dialogue screenshot"/>

<p>There are a number of configuration options available for the Web Profile
hub, connected with security.
They may be set on the hub command line, with the various <code>-web:*</code>
options, or using the <b>Profiles|Web Profile Configuration</b> menu.
The options are as follows:
</p>
<dl>
<dt><b>URL Controls:</b></dt>
<dd>Whether web clients are restricted from accessing sensitive resources,
    like local files, if they have not previously been mentioned in earlier
    SAMP messages.  This option is experimental, but it is probably a good
    idea to leave it on for security reasons.
    </dd>
<dt><b>CORS cross-domain access:</b></dt>
<dd>Whether to allow access using the Cross-Origin Resource Sharing standard.
    this is believed to be the safest mode of browser/hub communication,
    so it should usually be switched on.
    </dd>
<dt><b>Flash cross-domain access:</b></dt>
<dd>Whether to allow access using the Adobe Flash-based 
    <code>crossdomain.xml</code> mechanism.
    This may be less secure than CORS, but is required for
    some browser/web application combinations.
    If you use a browser that supports CORS
    (thought to be: Chrome v2.0+, Firefox v3.5+, Safari v4.0+, IE v8+),
    and only use JavaScript-based web SAMP applications, you may be able
    to leave this switched off and thereby improve security.
    </dd>
<dt><b>Silverlight cross-domain access</b></dt>
<dd>Whether to allow access using the Microsoft Silverlight-based
    <code>clientaccesspolicy.xml</code> mechanism.
    Silverlight is believed to support the Flash mechanism, so you can and
    should probably leave this switched off.
    </dd>
</dl>
<p>Note that the configuration options may only be changed when the
Web Profile itself is not running.
</p>

<p>You may be able to find an experimental 
<a href="http://www.star.bristol.ac.uk/~mbt/websamp/monitor.html"
   >Web Profile client</a> here.
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Web Profile Security">

<p>The JSAMP 1.3 Working Draft discusses security in relation to the 
Web profile to some extent, but notes that there are outstanding
security concerns, and that experimentation will continue in hub
implementations around this issue.
</p>

<p>The security measures taken by the JSAMP Web Profile implementation
relating to the Web Profile are:
</p>
<ul>
<li>In the default configuration, the Web Profile is switched off.
    Users can switch it on during hub operation using the <b>Profiles</b>
    menu from the hub GUI (if present).  It can also be switched on
    from the command-line or programatically at hub startup.
    The fact that it's off by default means that web clients will not be
    able to register unless the user has explicitly opted in, so only
    users who have some idea what the Web Profile is will be exposed to it
    at this stage.  This policy may be changed (Web Profile on by default)
    in future releases depending on how thinking on security progresses.
    </li>
<li>If the Web Profile is switched off during operation using
    the <b>Profiles|Web Profile</b> menu item in the hub GUI,
    any clients registered through the Web Profile will be 
    disconnected immediately.  A user can therefore eject Web Profile clients
    if there are suspicions about their behaviour.  Single clients can
    be ejected as well using the <b>Clients|Disconnect Selected Client</b>
    menu item.
    </li>
<li>The HTTP server on which the Web Profile runs rejects any access
    attempts from hosts other than the local host, as recommended by
    the SAMP 1.3 document.
    </li>
<li>The Web Profile URL translation service (Section 5.2.6 of SAMP 1.3)
    is, by default, selective about what URLs it will proxy.
    URLs are identified as local or non local; local ones are those using
    the file: protocol, or those using the http: protocol which point to
    the local host.  Non-local URLs are proxied without restriction.
    Local URL translation is only performed for a local URL if it has
    previously been mentioned (as the value of a Message or Response
    argument) by a non-Web Profile client; translation requests which
    do not meet this criterion are met with a 403 Forbidden response.
    This means for instance that a Web Profile client cannot simply
    request, e.g., the content of <code>file:///etc/passwd</code>.
    This policy does not constitute bulletproof protection of local
    resources to malicious web-profile clients, but it does guard against
    some straightforward attacks.
    This policy is on by default, but can be switched off and on using
    the <b>Profiles|Web Profile Configuration|URL Controls</b> menu item from
    the hub GUI, or with the <code>-web:[no]urlcontrol</code> hub
    command-line switch.
    </li>
<li>The details of which cross-domain workarounds are used can be controlled
    from the <b>Profiles|Web Profile Configuration</b> menu or from the
    hub command line.  The different workarounds can be switched on and off
    independently, though only while the Web Profile is not running.
    By default CORS and Flash are switched on, and Silverlight is switched off.
    </li>
</ul>

</subsection>

</section>
</body>
</document>
